hello I'm your host David Barnard and my
guest today is Thomas pedit an
independent consultant focused on
subscription app growth across
acquisition activation and
monetization over the past decade Thomas
has worked with hundreds of clients and
help manage nine digits in ad spin with
a positive return on the podcast I
talked with Thomas about how to find
success with web to app the value and
challenges of owning the transaction and
why avoiding App Store fees isn't a
great reason to experiment with web to
app but might work out anyway Hey Thomas
Thanks so much for coming back on the
podcast I think it's your third or
fourth time we'll just have to make it
an annual tradition yeah my pleasure
always happy to be back and uh you you
have a great audience and uh I I I
really enjoy the the other guest and the
the rest of the podcast so I'm really
happy to bring my small contribution
here yeah well you're you're episodes
are some of the more popular so it's
selfish of me to to get you back on
since uh people seem to really enjoy
your insights and you know for those who
haven't heard Thomas before you know
he's been Consulting for what almost a
decade now and worked on multiple
subscription apps and worked with so
many different teams and what I love
about Thomas and other folks who work
across a lot of teams and I've said this
a lot on the podcast so reiterating for
those who've heard this but you know he
you just get so much experience and and
you see what works in one app and then
you try it in another and it doesn't
work and it really gives you a deeper
understanding of some of these topics to
be trying these things across so many
different apps versus
maybe some bias that comes across when
you've only ever worked on a single app
and so it's great to get your insights
uh you know as you work with so many
different apps um so this year it's
2024 and one of the topics I'm getting
asked about a ton and just see more and
more conference talks about see more and
more tools popping up
um is web to app so first I find that
like term confusing so let's just Define
what do what do we mean with web to app
because there even are like multiple
ways multiple kind of paths that that
people use Under the Umbrella of webt so
what what is webt what do we what do we
mean by that there definitely a
definitely a wide umbrella like there's
lots of subtopics in there I think the
the the low down is a a lot of app
developers they're the most of the
marketing is driving straight to the App
Store where regardless if it's paid
marketing or or else and different
channels and I guess web to app is the
way developers would bring this traffic
first on some kind of web page that can
be more or less sophisticated can be
very simple just a landing page that
then drives to the app store or can be
very sophisticated have the the whole
arding and maybe the payment maybe the
sign up maybe even part of the the
actual app experience some features on
the web but in the end they still want
to drive to the app at some point and I
guess it's a very good place that we
start there because one of the reason
that it's it's becoming such a hot up I
mean it's not new but it's definitely
more in the raer of everybody is that
there is Big opportunities in driving
traffic on the web rather than on the
stores that are a number of limitation
if only just the layout you can't show
whatever you want to people who interact
with uh whatever content you put out
there whether it's an app or not so more
flexibility more
channels but in the end most of the time
developers are interested to get user in
the app because uh the native experience
might be better in a number of case uh
but also because it offers retention
levels that website just don't like in
particular being on the home screen even
if you could put a uh a screen a
shortcut nobody does or having the push
notification even if they exist on on
websites it's just not the same power
like it's clear that retention long-term
retention is is higher to handle uh in
an app and the experience is great it
doesn't mean that the experience has to
start with the app and I think that's
what the web to app Encompass yeah I
like that you started there because one
of the things I have heard from a lot of
folks is that they they feel like they
need to build a a full-fledged web app
to even experiment with web to app um
and and and right off the bat it's like
no it can be as simple as just a landing
page like you said where you're able to
collect attribution more uh
deterministically on the web so you know
I mean I think for a lot of apps it
would be tough to make that funnel work
you know dropping people onto web page
and then just immediately sending them
to the App Store um but for some maybe
maybe that does work but it but it does
kind of span the gamut from that kind of
landing page where you craft your
message more directly and specifically
maybe more interactive Maybe video and
stuff that you just don't get when you
drop somebody onto the app store and
then it goes all the way to like
providing a much more sophisticated
experience or even a a full-fledged web
app um and and one thing to kind of
pause here too is that I think you know
it just it's so contextual like it just
depends so much on the app the
experiences and even some of what you
were saying about um retention it that's
probably not true of every app like some
apps might act depending on exactly like
Photo room I've actually been using
photo room more on the desktop than I do
on my phone because I use it
specifically for subclub like I'd use it
for removing backgrounds of guest photos
and things like that and so you know
everything we talk about everything is
so contextual but I think that's an
important thing to bring up even as
we're just starting this conversation is
that that everything we we talk about in
web to app is going to be so contextual
that you what's working for one app
things we maybe even suggest may not
work for you um so I think it's a great
place to start of like the the breadth
of of context the bread of of options
for web to app um I think that the next
place to go with that is is why like why
why do webt and we kind of hinted a
little bit but like why don't you list
out some of the reasons and we can kind
of dig into some of those yeah I I'll
intervene back uh on on on the breath
before I go to the why the sort of the
the context behind it is exactly where
where I was going to go in the sense
that I've seen I've seen different apps
succeed or fail with completely
different setups on web to app uh I I
know of a gaming company that has one of
these very very simple learning page
it's just like and it enables them to
like do attribution differently explain
also the game in a way that the in the
in the store they couldn't like because
the the the graphic is full screen and
so on like but then this simple landing
page scheme didn't work for a number of
my other apps and then you've got the
whole like it's not just a landing page
or fully developed on boarding there's
many ch Shades of Gray in between I can
remember one project in particular where
we're like okay what if we put the sign
up or we don't what if we put the
payment or we don't and the answer was
always is it depends like so there's
context depending on what your app is
doing like for example n as a as an
onboarding on the web that is 50 screens
I bet if photo room was doing that it
wouldn't work at all so highly depends
on on on what you're doing um sometimes
you can just showcase the AA moment very
fast like and and that's typically the
case for for photo room H sometimes you
really really want to drive to the
payment because that's that's your main
reason to go to to the web because you
want to charge there it doesn't need to
be one way or the other and I think it
goes Way Beyond the app itself and the
vertical you're in but actually the
context of how that user I've heard
about my app and if I take for example
blinkist which was one of the Pioneers
in in web2 app and I remember copying
the tactics back in
2016 so they're like sort of eight years
ago they were already doing work to up
and blink is does a lot of other things
but they they parly cracked uh presence
on tabula and out Brin what I call pay
content marketing but those sites the
context of these ads that is placed
typically next to um news content or
similar they drive to a page that looks
like an article and brings like it's a
completely different way of doing web to
app because they KN they understood how
to adjust to the context of how their ad
was placed what are the user expecting
when they're clicking on this and what
they want to see and I bet if they were
pulling just the full web em booding
that they do have for this context it
wouldn't work and then when the traffic
is coming from Facebook uh the
experience that you have in the website
of of blinket is completely different
from the one if you click on an outbrain
ad so the the cont goes definitely by by
vertical what works for gaming wouldn't
work for for dating or for Fitness but
also uh you have to adjust and in a
perfect world is you have these
different tools and experiences journe
user Journeys available and you find out
that yeah for this particular ad
placement this this journey just works
the best and and I think that's where
the Pioneers ended up in the sense of of
course it's easier to just have one web
flow and drive everything to it but
you're probably stalling compared to the
opportunity you could have of if
somebody's searching me on Google or if
somebody's clicking from a Tik Tok or if
somebody like you is is looking for
photo room uh desktop experience because
it's from sub Club you have to offer
them something different and actually in
the case of photo room I think they put
like at least 10 free tools on on the
website that are in the app and at the
beginning I was like I don't know why
they're doing it I don't have enough
internal information about this but I
was like wow this looks really
cannibalization because I'm doing
something on the web without any kind of
log in anything just really one off and
I'm lost but in the end if you look I do
believe it's it's beneficial because
they're playing the long game and see
you you memorize it you know the app is
there if you need it you know there are
other features in there and I think for
them it's like a very long game
acquisition Channel where actually you
have experienced the feature on the web
but one day you might need more and you
know the app is there with more it's
just they don't need the conversion
instantly they can like I believe it's a
it's a long game in this case that not
everybody can do that and not everybody
can offer the full feature on the web
which they manage to do very nicely uh
but I think it does reinforce a lot like
yeah context context context of what
you're doing what's your strategy and
how why why is the user Landing there
and actually adjust to it it's just like
there there's many ways of apprach this
so let's talk about
why people are doing it like why web to
app and I mean again like we've already
hinted at it but um what are the kind of
primary motivations and then then how do
we see that play out and then we can
kind of take them one by
one that that's a good one because I've
I mean I've said it before but I believe
people are going web to have for the
wrong reason but then eventually on the
way they discover that there is an
opportunity that is not necessarily the
one that that they imagine two two of
the very clear reason that people are oh
we want to do web to app or we need to
do web to app is one the store fees like
the commission that Apple and Google are
taking on on subscription or I APS or 15
or 30% depending the case and then when
you process this payment on the web ER
you'd pay something around 3% via stripe
or similar so 3% 30% there's a 10x Gap
and you you see a lot of post explaining
web to up like oh you can save all of
the fees it's not technically true like
because there is a fee and the Gap is
not as big as people think I believe
this reason is not a good one uh there
is less fees but actually the the whole
funnel looks very different and you
can't fully expect the same conversion
rate the same retention rate like every
every metric would move typically when
you're trying to charge on the web is
much harder to get people to pay uh
because there's not the trust factor of
Apple because you have to pull your
credit card er because like there are
many reason that makes that uh people
will just the uix you know in the app is
just great like okay subscribe for trial
yes face ID whatever and you're in which
is a huge Advantage for but then even
after the transaction a lot of people
are like oh I have a cost of acquisition
of of 50 on the web web and 30 in the
app or whatever or vice versa I'm like
yeah but the customers are not worth the
exact same like the renewal rates are
going to be different the refund rate is
going to be different uh the fact that
you own the transaction because you're
the one processing it for me is a big
plus of doing web to up and people are
like the fee the fee the fee I mean
there is a value in owning the the
customer relationship rather than
delegating it to Apple um so see but
there's also a lot of work
the transition I think a lot of people
kind of
underestimate the the um involuntary
turn because you know people are
incentivized to keep their credit cards
updated with apple whereas like each
customer that you have that individual
transaction with you need Dunning like
you need to be able to email them and
say update your credit card when it
expires and like it's yeah there's also
a lot of work in owning that transition
but there's value in it and so that but
it's trade-offs and I I think that's
where there there maybe has been some
naivity in the conversation around web
to app of like oh yeah save on fees save
on fees but then not like talking about
the practicalities like you are here of
like everything's a trade-off you'll
probably experience lower conversion but
maybe you'll have higher retention you
may you know save on fees but you're GNA
have to like Implement a lot of
infrastructure around Dunning and other
things and so it's like everything's a
trade-off and you need to really
understand the depths of some of that
before you go just jump on the web to
app uh uh Trend or whatever yeah
absolutely you know a lot of people
saying calling the fee a tax you know is
the Apple tax is the 30% and I I'm not
really known for defending the Platforms
in general but I I I do believe there is
real value behind the commission like
the visibility that the App Store is
giving you the fact that they're
processing the uh the tax for you the
fact that they're processing refunds and
like the billing errors and so on there
there is real value it so maybe some
people can argue that this value is not
the gap between 30% and 3% and and I
would agree and I think if Apple had
lowered the fee to
10% many less people would be doing less
to up because the value is really big so
and and many people who move to web to
up underestimate the amount of work that
it is going to represent to maintain
this this I mean there is a value in
owning this relationship but it it it
translate into into work definitely yeah
one of the more subtle things too is
that both Apple and Google I think
accept over 200 forms of payment across
so like you know even stripe or paddle
or or a lot of these Alternatives that
people are using on the web you don't
have 200 different payment options and
like you know somebody in you know
Africa wants to pay with the the the
carrier billing and apple supports that
it's like Apple and Google have gone you
know they understand billing in all
these countries both from like the
retail presence and their and how big
the app store is at volume and they year
in year out are adding more and more
options in those localities in those in
those
localities in those different countries
to uh allow the payment uh processors
and the and the how people like to pay
in those countries and so even subtle
things like that that you know you think
oh I'll just you know again save the fee
but it's like the they do a lot to earn
the fee U maybe not 30% like you said
and then if you're a Netflix it's like
you have a big enough team where you can
start expanding into all these different
payment options in those countries and
you do it in the order of like what the
highest value countries are the US is
obviously the easiest it's just credit
card and stripe and Apple pay even um
but once you start you know making once
you're as you get bigger and the
opportunities are bigger in these
smaller countries then having 200
different payment options it's actually
really important and and very valuable
yeah and I think that that's the reason
Google has put in particular I mean
Apple too but Google has made an
incredible effort to to expand payments
and it's it's extremely relevant given
the the penetration of under in in
markets where alternative payment system
are are much pretty much the norm rather
than than an exception and it's true
that from a US perspective or even in
some of the Western Europe countries
like yeah everybody have great card why
would I want to support anything maybe
PayPal and that's it but there are many
countries where it's not like this at
all like and even even culturally is not
like this it's not only like banking
access but really like oh I'm used to
pay with this system and and that's it
and then every country has like their
own like er I moved to Portugal last
year and I I was very surprised at the
amount of transaction that people are
doing through a system that's called MBA
that I've never heard before or
elsewhere and for them it's just normal
it's just easier and you increase the
potential that if if you support this
that people are going to pay but then
maybe netx can but which developer can
go and say okay Portugal has MB and then
India has this and then Spain has bom
and then in Argentina they want car
building and then there they have this
prepaid car that are very big like no
it's very hard to get there and and it
will affect your conversion so I don't
think there is also value and it's it's
where again contextual comes back you
know in terms of of the vertical in
terms of the user Journey but also in
understanding actually that user are
maybe better off converting them in the
app because of where they're located
because I'm not offering this and and
you have this this situation where you
have to decide almost in real time based
on test usually but like oh I've
identified that this this segment of
user I'm actually better off go moving
them to iip even if the fees is there
but but this particular group of user
probably not because they can pay with
Apple pay on the website and the
friction to the conversion is going to
be minimal and and so for me it's it's
never been too much about should I
charge in the app or on the web the
answer is nestly both is in which case
you're doing it and through which
Journey which makes it a lot more
complicated obviously to figure out but
that's how you also discover new new
maximums for for different
segments yeah I I think the the best
advice I've heard on this too is like
that the absolute highest level um way
to sort those two is if you have any
understanding of the level of intent and
kind of to your point earlier like if
somebody is searching your brand on
Google then they probably have pretty
high intent and you can funnel that to
the web and not expect as high of a dip
in conversion um promotions if you're
offering you know 50% off send those
people to the web they have very high
intent you're offering a huge discount
um you know I think those kind of things
um at a very high level make a lot of
sense but then like you said once you
then start testing there's a lot more
Nuance of who to send where which and
then it's contextual like you know we
can give advice but every app needs to
to try and and see what works in their
particular context and for different
personas so the fact that every app
needs to test this on their own actually
leads to maybe the next biggest and
maybe the most important reason to
consider web to app is attribution it's
like in order to do these tests you need
to be able to like understand the users
better and you definitely have an
advantage on the web for that tell tell
me about attribution and web tab yeah so
we started saying the first one is avoid
the fee and I did develop that I don't
think it's a good reason but you still
should go on the web and the the
attribution is definitely the other
reason like people being frustrated by
SKR Network or limitation on what I call
measurement I never said tracking but uh
of tracking and uh and uh yeah oh on the
web we don't have this restriction let's
go on the web I think this is not
entirely true in the sense that it's not
as simple as on the web you can do
whatever for attribution and especially
the transition from being on a browser
on the web and then people would get to
the app and you have to reconciliate
this is not as straightforward as it
seems there are also restriction that do
apply on the web that Safar is blocking
third party cookies and that I mean a
lot a lot of like new restrictions it's
not as straightforward as people think
and they often discover like oh
attribution is actually not perfect
there either here's the news attribution
is never perfect so yes there are things
that you can do on the web that have too
many that have limitations on in the app
and especially on on the Apple side uh
but it's not as simple and as
straightforward as people think and even
though over time like things got better
I think the Pioneers here had a lot of
surprise on the way when they move to
attribution and even I sometimes you
discover like specific setups from
people I'm like oh wait a second what do
we do in this case like it's not like
it's it's like the easy way of okay I
moov to the web I have attribution back
and we roll like it's kind of a quite
complex topic where attribution also
becomes not fully comparable which is a
tricky one because then you want to
compare your different Journeys together
and then attribution is not there's a
lot of progress that has been made and
uh in particular at networks uh
implementing conversion apis that do
cross the barrier between browsers and
and app a lot better than it used to but
it's not as straightforward as there's
always work around they always have been
but they're not as simple as people
think so for me going because you're
frustrated of a SC network uh is not a
great reason because you're also going
to face
restriction in eventually it leads
people to experiment with where to up
and they discover that there are
opportunities that there are obstacles
with attribution but there are
opportunities so it doesn't really
matter why people go that route uh but
for me it's never going to be about the
fear or about attribution and and a lot
of the reason is exactly what you
explained before about contextuality is
that that kind of user
can be converted on the web at a very
high rate because they're coming from
Brand search or maybe virality or a
particular coupon or whatever but there
are also reason that people never go to
web to app for initially and that
actually have massive benefit and one
one uh one that I quote quite regularly
is audience expansion uh even on
Facebook like Facebook doesn't show to
the same people your ads if they're
directed to the store or to the web
based on how people interacted with with
the different kind of ads before based
on propensity that they judge that at
this point of time that user may convert
better here and there and in the end of
the day I want both so I'm better of
running and and I know those running web
to app at scale it's never like they're
spending 100% on on on web acquisition
or 100% on the app it's always an and
never or uh because of these kind of
Mechanics for audience expansion but
also sometimes a specific Channel like
for example uh on Google search you have
to buy it together if you direct into
the store together with some YouTube and
display inventory but maybe you want to
manage your own keywords uh on the web
but then when you buy search on traffic
you can't be buying it for only iOS you
have to buy the twoos so like it's kind
of H so you can do that on YouTube
specifically for example so YouTube is a
very interesting case where you have to
buy it bundled uh in the case of of the
stores but then you have a lot more GR
it if you're buying web inventory from
YouTube directly because then you can
specify the device you can block
channels you can say okay I don't want I
don't want to be shown on these channels
you can select some audiences that you
wouldn't be able to do on on Google app
ads but then Google app ads also work
and I I have one particular case on on
YouTube where we're running YouTube ads
that go to a web flow and we're running
Google app ads the UAC ads and they tend
to attract a slly different audience but
also not necessarily be shown on the
same channel or not be shown at the same
time so here for me definitely like
audience expansion I had another case
that for a while when ATT come up uh
Pinterest went out completely of the
store acquisition like they removed
their ad product that was directing to
the store because they didn't want to
adjust to uh Apple new system so you
could only direct to web pages
eventually Pinterest has bring back
their app product but for for for a
while if you wanted to advertise on
Pinterest you had to do it on the web
and maybe for some people Pinterest is a
bit of a secondary thought and like not
really big but actually the audience on
on pest is very big and extremely
valuable like majority iOS very big
penetration in the US especially among
let's say 30 to 50 years old women which
is like a highly thought after audience
for many subscription apps and so now
Pinterest has bringing it back so my
case is maybe less convincing than
before but like it it does talk to
audience expansion whether the network
has the two option or not uh for me this
is the two reason that audience
expansion but also offering the best
Journey at the right time to every users
and that can only be done by having
different ones uh so yeah it's never
going to be zero or 100 but
rather a mix of of Both Worlds so before
we move on from attribution I I would
like to actually talk through some
specific examples
of how it works and why it works and and
I'll go first so the the example I'd
love to give is uh Greg Stewart was on
the podcast uh he runs an app called
ladder actually one of our more popular
episodes if you haven't heard that go go
back and search for for Greg Stewart
ladder on the podcast in the way they're
using web to app I I I think it's like
one of the great examples
of H how and why
attribution can be improved through web
to app so what they're doing is they're
sending um a lot of their traffic but to
your point not all their traffic to the
web from ads on Instagram and Tik Tok
and what they do is that they do a
survey and
and I think he told me on the podcast
that by like question six of the survey
they have a really good understanding of
like what Persona that is and like
How likely that Persona is to pay and so
by question six they're able to send
feedback back to the Tik Tok algorithm
back to the Instagram algorithm to say
hey this is a really high value user
send me more like this and that that
quick feedback from the ad being shown
to hey this is a high value user is
really really strong in optimizing those
algorithms to find more people like that
um but interestingly and and Greg and I
were just having drinks a few weeks ago
he lives here in my area and uh we're
talking about doing a follow-up podcast
because they they've learned a whole lot
more in the in the year since we did
that episode and and one of the things
he was telling me is they most of their
revenue is still iOS so they're not
actually charging on the web but they're
doing the survey on the web and then
their their attribution is super fuzzy
in that they don't have perfect tracking
to your point earlier they don't have
perfect tracking from the web to the the
actual app installed to the payment but
because that survey is so dialed in and
getting that feedback so quickly that's
the leverage for them in web to app it's
not reducing the fees it's not um
perfect attribution through the whole
funnel um it's not payment on the web
it's it's it's just being able to get
the feedback to the algorithms more
directly and more uh
deterministically in that short window
to optimize the algorithm so like that's
an example of a web to app flow that has
a very
specific reason and a very specific
leverage Point that's working really
well for them in their context of a
fitness app where you can ask a bunch of
questions where user intents is high and
like you know the Ducks are in a row for
it to work but that's why it works do
you have any other examples like that of
very specific web app flows and here's
how they do it here's why they do it
here's why it works um we've kind of
hinted at some of them but I'd love to
get some like more concrete tactical
like here's how it actually
works yeah sure um like the example you
you're you're giving is very good
because at the end of the day like a lot
of a lot of a lot of acquisition is
driven by paid and a lot of paid is
driven by Instagram and Tik Tok uh and
there are basically only two levels to
make acquisition work one is get better
creative that catch the attention of
people and stop them on the feed and
make them want to experience whatever
you have to for them and the other one
is the quality of the signals that
you're sending back it's not about my
campaign structure is better and I've
got a hack and I've got the like there's
no hack like the hack is is sending
better signals early of differentiating
quality like early is really important
like um and that that makes me go
towards the end of what I had in in mind
is when SK Network came in a lot of
gaming folks like in subscription were
sort of gifted because a lot of the at
least the free trials but a lot of the
subscriptions start on the on the first
day of experience so when SC Network
came in we had this restriction that the
signal had to be send within 24 hours
and and for subscription I was like okay
I've got 70 % of my subscription
starting on Day Zero so actually is not
a major blocker even though I'm blind on
the trial conversion and I'm blind on
the what I call the late conversion the
ones that don't happen on day Zero but
in the gaming space it's very rare that
the transaction happen on day Zero and
you need like this day seven or day30 de
cohort development to understand the
quality and with this restriction of of
of at and the SC Network a lot of gaming
folks actually redesign their day Zero
experience so that they have the signals
that they can send back early enough to
to Facebook and this is a a really good
case where marketing actually had to
tweak Force tweak the product into I
need to get a hint and it's not about
making people pay on the first day it's
about qualifying different segments of
propensity to pay in the future so so
they they they tweaked a little bit so I
think this was a great example but you
asked for for something very specific so
I'll move there um the the fitness space
is one of the the typical that move to
web toab because you have like the level
of intent where you can ask this very
long flow of questions and you can
qualify people very well that's why n
has like 50 screens and it still work
and in other context it doesn't work I I
have a I have a it's it's a funny case
because I I work with two apps in the
same space like there there's sort of a
couple therapy uh a couple therapy app
but rather on the premium side of it
sort of it's pricey but it's very high
quality it's not like gimicky or
anything and it's the kind of things
were're actually moving directly to the
store there is a bit of friction in the
sense of do I really need that like not
only it looks expensive but also it
looks the very serious answer straight
on and what what we noticed early on is
that in acquisition that that was going
to be a major blocker because what they
show in the in the ad is not necessarily
super catchy and then the problem is
hard is not necessarily something you
want to do at any point so it was a
major obstacle but then they realize
they can drive a flow where we can start
in a much softer way more like a miname
and something that is not so let's say
stressful than thinking that your
relationship is failing but rather
taking on the fun side and actually we
brainstorm about oh let's do another app
that would be very simple and much more
gim like gaming and we can make fun ads
and then it's going to be cheap because
everybody's going to click to play and
our monetization scheme is actually that
this is a lead provider for the main app
where we're going to have a minority of
users that were already qualified that
we can lead there they eventually
decided not to build a second app but to
do this flow on the web and it makes a
lot of sense because those sort of mini
games uh it's very flexible to build
them on the wayb so some people do quiz
can be a mini game can be like sort of a
playable game but it can very often
leads into quiz where instead of putting
the questions of a fitness app it sort
of funny quiz and you want to complete
it so those can be a lot more catchy to
put in the ad but then people complete
it at a high rate because it's very easy
and slowly slowly you move into where
you're actually going that if you had
put it it in the first place straight up
might not have worked I had one success
case with with this which was in the
brain trining brain sorry brain training
space uh which eventually become very
normal to do this so the extreme version
of it would be a sort of this this very
aggressive ads of what's your IQ or or
have you do you have a higher IQ than
your neighbor and then they start making
like very easy question quiz there is a
sort of a mini game that you start oh
you actually look like you're 5% over
everybody but let's figure it out or
let's train yourself to get to the 20%
and then they lead you to the app where
they have all these kind of mini games
and eventually the monetization there
was there in their case the web to
upflow not only that doesn't need the
payment to be there but certainly would
be counterproductive because the whole
thing is about uh really engagement and
about sort of warming up the audience
like uh many ads that are directing to
the store they're made for very
straightforward funnels where you see
the ad you want it you get into it you
go to the onboarding and you're going to
subscribe straight up after 10 minutes
but a lot of use case do not fit this
journey and this is where the web offer
a much more flexible experience of
having a warm up before before you even
send to the store where there is a big
drop off in conversion because people
are looking at your screenshot and
making a decision and they need to
confirm and so on like uh or maybe uh in
the kids app space for example you'd
have like this parental gate to install
an app but maybe you can show the kids
the content that you have whether it's
videos or games without having this and
once this sort of first touch Point has
been made and sort of oh yeah this is
really interesting then then bring sort
of the friction step that can be a sign
up that can be a download is a friction
step and obviously a payment is a
friction step so it can be web to web is
a very good way when you have a product
that is hard to sell in an instant like
obviously I don't know I I sit for the
room I I want to remove my background
I'm motivated I download the app I start
the freight Tri because I want to remove
the logo a perfect case to have like
direct to store Journeys but some of the
harder case were typically in finance
also like uh lot of like there's a lot
of friction in in at many steps of
making the decision but also plugging my
cards like a lot of things and some of
just just need to be warm up before they
go to these high friction points and I
think those are very good use case to go
web to yeah that's really great and one
one thing you kind of dropped in there
which I hadn't thought about until you
mentioned it is that there's maybe even
and I I think it's improved over the
last decade but the there's still kind
of a perception that apps should be
cheap and so maybe that's another place
where like when you do have a very
expensive product you're able to
position it better in some ways on the
web where people just don't expect an
app to be hundreds of dollars or you
know $50 a month or things like that and
that may be another great place to
experiment with web to app is being able
to better position and better filter for
purchase intent of these something that
is much more expensive I have something
very specific here is that not not all
of them and my couple therapy app
actually is not this kind because is
very much something that is personal and
b2c but I have different apps that have
like sort of a somewhere in between b2c
and B2B use case like uh small teams
smbs and there is one thing that is very
limiting when you pay in the App Store
is the billing when you're a
professional and even even as an
employee like oh yeah I need this for
work but then it's my account on my
phone how do I build a company or we're
small team and and and I've seen I'm
thinking about one in particular but I'm
sorry I don't want to quote it h where
they actually had this restriction
because they had lots of small teams
that were like we want to use your
product together but we can't pay it
through and we want to pay for it and we
don't care about the price and it can be
1050 or 100 that we still want it but we
need it to go through the billing of
whatever HR wants and there is a process
and whatever that can be handled on the
web but cannot be handled when you use
iaps and this is a very good case to go
web to app not because the fee is lower
just because this is what the customer
need they need to have an invoice that
is not in the name then in the name of
the company and so on so yes maybe for
Price your product but I can't see how
many price your product can have this
component of it's not only for me but
it's in the the in the context of a
professional use or semi-professional
use because sometimes the lines are very
blurred this day of of prosumers or and
so on where billing becomes important
and yeah I don't want it I don't want it
on my app store account because then I
can't deduce the tax or I can't charge
it to my client or whatever the
situation is yeah I've been man I've
been bugging Apple for years about this
apple specifically I don't think Google
handles it any better either but and and
I run into this all the time I have a
revenue cat Apple account specifically
because there were like two pieces of
software that I needed from the Mac App
Store and I had to go set up a whole
account put my Revenue cat credit card
in now it's like orphaned in there like
I guess they'll can like if I ever leave
Revenue cat they'll cancel the card and
it'll just startop billing or whatever
but it's like so confusing and such a
pain in the butt to do that and then
even on my personal App Store account
there's apps that I buy for work and for
the last you know 16 years years that
I've been uh building apps it's like
this is my profession and I specifically
buy apps and subscribe to apps to learn
from them and so man it's so tricky and
I mean I
probably I I end up charging a lot of my
app store stuff to my business card
because most of what I do on the App
Store but then sometimes like the kids
purchase a game and then it ends up on
that car like it's a freaking disaster
like trying to manage all that so yes
exactly L right I wish the app stores
handled this sort of thing better
offering you know multiple credit cards
on a single account and the option to
like switch between them when you're
billing and like so many things that
they could make better on the the b2c uh
uh B2B use case specifically um so yeah
another another really good concrete
example of a reason to to use webt yeah
I I I have one that is not B2B but maybe
it's a good time like to also mention it
like I I I started before like when we
mentioned the fee like owning the
transaction is important sometimes for
the investors or whatever but sometimes
just for optimization purpose and I
remember one case in particular where we
we were charging a number of
subscriptions through the web like we
had a mix like some subscription came
from iip and some came on the web and we
disc so at some point people churn like
no matter how good your app is you're
you're going to have uh payment sh uh
sometimes voluntary payment sh like uh
people want to unsubscribe and whenever
people had like so when it was in the
App Store well people want to have
subscribe they go to the settings they
unsubscribe which is there are more
problems than that but we had this flow
when people had had pay on the web that
whenever they were going to unsubscribe
we're making it very easy to them but
then there was one screen before they
confirm which was like okay so you can't
confirm it's this button but here's a
cont offer and we refund you half of
what you already paid
and you keep the subscription live but
we keep the other half and there was a
massive amount of people who were about
to churn they were like oh yeah that's a
great deal I'll take it and this is
something that I can't do on the app
store because I don't have the
flexibility of owning the transaction
and and and doing whatever I want so I'm
not I'm not forcing people to own the
transaction so that they can do like
very tricky unsubscribe flows which I I
think is terrible but be illegal in most
countries pretty soon I mean the even
work out laws around that yeah but in
this case I think it was a win-win you
know the users who decided to get half
in refund and half as a discount they
were super happy to continue and us it
was Revenue that materialized that would
have vanished so I think everybody was
happy in this case yeah no that's a
really fantastic example I never heard
of anybody actually offering to refund
like the whole you know next year 50%
off can be a huge incentive but then
actually refunding that's that's a
that's bold but yeah I can see how that
worked I I you I haven't seen much but I
remember when we made the math for us it
was beneficial but and also we had like
really good feedback about it like not
only it was financially interesting but
those people who churn they kept a very
good image of us because we told you
want to you want to stop stop no problem
like click that button that's it but
they were surprised positively by it and
eventually we had a quite decent
retention on on this segment yeah that's
so cool um see you hinted at it but one
of the other reasons we were going to
talk about for trying web to app was
Channel expansion so you you've hinted
at that a little bit but I wanted to go
a little more in depth about why web to
app is important when you are expanding
channels yeah I think I mentioned it
briefly
but you as you scale up like
advertising sometime you just hit
Plateau like and there is there is a
certain volume that depends on every app
because of the the audience obviously
where there just a diminishing return on
on every additional dollar that you're
putting in there and I mean if you're
starting and you haven't hit like limits
like this I would question if you should
put so much effort into expanding
towards web to app as you haven't let's
say exploited all you can in the easier
route but there is a moment where having
even on the same network like campaigns
that run on both is beneficial because
because the maybe the user can go to the
store but maybe they they they need like
this sort of warmup that we talked
before and it can for me it's mainly
because it's different users that that
are going to click on one and the other
but it can perfectly be one user in a
different moment of their time and
Facebook is actually really good at
noticing or predicting like oh that user
at that time is going to convert better
on that flow and this is why when when
you look at at the in Facebook in
particular you look at your potential
audience reach so maybe you've selected
I don't know I want to advertise in half
the states only to women everybody over
21 years old like not not interest
targeting but like simple targeting like
this and and it's iOS only and then
you've got like okay there's 50 million
people or there's 20 million people
fitting your your targeting description
and then you run that campaign for a
while even at very big scale people
spending five digits a day and like oh
over six months my total reach is two
million people out of an audience of 20
million just because Facebook doesn't
want to show the ad Those ads to the
rest because they think they're not
suitable they're not they're not going
to convert or because of whatever reason
maybe they're preserving the inventory
for others
having web ads even when you run it on
similar creative just the fact that the
signal that you're sending back is
different is going to trigger Facebook
to show it to different people and
typically a lot of the apps I work with
we're not using the same creative on the
web flow as we're using on the app on
the this the call to action is different
the wording is different the experience
weer is different so we also adjust the
creative a little bit and and we end up
having a total brid that is
significantly higher that if we running
only the web the web campaign or only
the app campaign and this is where for
me it's really a case of I want to do
both because the audience expansion is
not oh there's more audience that is
going to click on the web than on the
app no it's just there's more audience
when you run the two in parallel there
are people that never click on app
install ads on on meta and meta sees it
so they stop showing ads to them uh for
insource because after they seen 50 ads
towards this store and they haven't
click on one Facebook preserves this
inventory for something that is more
likely to generate value elsewhere and
but for me this is a this is one of the
core reason going to web to app like
just because I'm going to reach more
people and because I'm going to have the
opportunity to convert users that would
never have even seen my ads if I were
doing it only on the direct r or or if I
was doing it only on the web for that
purpose the the exact same logic Works
uh on the other side as well yeah and
then it opens up new channels too right
like blinket you talked about tabula
like doing doing sending people from
tabula into the App Store probably is I
don't know if it's even possible or like
you were talking about Pinterest for a
long time didn't even have um app
install ads um so Channel expansion is
important too not just audio expansion
on the existing channels which that's
really interesting I never heard anybody
talk about that um but but yeah tell me
more about some channels that you're
able to experiment with and even maybe
some specific channels you've seen be
successful um that just wouldn't even
work sending them to the App Store yeah
so for me the the the three very big
ones here they're Google search er
YouTube and tabula andrain that I I I
group together actually the merger was
consell I think they they were they
should have merged and they didn't but
doesn't matter I I I merged them because
the let's say the the logic is very
similar and so on those sort of so
Google search and YouTube you just can't
buy it the same way on the app side and
uh it is it is those are very good if
you want to only if you want to separate
brand search from competitor search and
generic search and actually show them
something different a different USB you
just can't do that on the on Google adad
so uh there is a very good reason also
to control your budget a little bit more
and so on in the case of outb and tabula
at some point they did add like an app
uh product where whenever you were
clicking there it was actually going to
the store to my knowledge that product
didn't work very well at all I don't
know if it even still exists or not I'm
not I'm I'm not sure but I remember
perfectly that during a long time it was
just there but nobody was using it and I
mean we tried back then when it like we
were a group of three Berlin startup
that were very big clients of both SBR
and tabul so that was blink uh eight fit
where I was and babble which is also has
a very significant Budget on on the web
I'm not sure I should be saying it but
then then other client is Babble is
spending the vast majority of their ad
spend on on web acquisition even
actually I interviewed the senior VP of
marketing uh and he he talked very
specifically about how much they're
doing not app specific and so that'll be
the podcast that precedes this one
actually okay so I'm not revealing
anything confidential let's go check
that podcast this is perfect but uh yeah
and I remember we were chatting like so
the three of us about oh have you tried
the new product and for all of us three
it was like this product just didn't
work maybe it was the early days what I
strongly believe is that sending to the
store just doesn't work in the context
of outr and tabula ads because of the
nature of the ads like people are not
expecting to land on the store and we're
like trying to get more and more obious
like putting screenshot in the creative
and saying it's an app and download the
app in the text and like because our
conversion rate in the store to install
was really low on this and there was no
there was no amount of forcing the
creative to prepare the user that was
going to the store that was going to
work and in this case it's clear that a
web funnel is a lot more suitable than
going to the straight to the store like
it's just the nature of the placement
makes it there there are other smaller
cases but I think they're less relevant
one because they're smaller and two
because over time they did add the app
product so that was the case for
Pinterest that bring it back that's the
case for Reddit as well and I do believe
that Reddit is a little bit more like
outand and tabula in the sense of
sending the user straight from Reddit to
the
store you're going to have to be very
creative about what you're putting in
the in the ad for it to work the the
context of Reddit is so particular that
the ads that work typically don't look
like an ad that is going that is going
to convert immediately like and there I
I'm pretty convinced that the
flexibility of showing different steps
to the user and having sort of a a
transition between the ad and what
you're actually selling is of extreme
importance it's not like I'm on the
Instagram feed and seeing something and
I'm used to clicking and I know I'm
going to go there and you you have you
you can see how Facebook grew their ad
product really nicely because they manag
to have like this sort of uh Habit of
user of they know and especially for
gaming like uh there lot gaming ads were
particularly efficient on on on Facebook
and Instagram for for a very long time
because the context was there but try
putting a gaming ad on on Reddit or
Pinterest that's not going to work for
sure um so I think in this case it's
really the the context of the ad itself
no matter what you do like what you do
also matters but it's really the context
of the ad that matters so yeah and this
audience expansion and channel expansion
for me it's threefold like audience
reach that is better doing both some
channels just don't offer the same
product or the channel doesn't work
because of the ad context and those are
three very good reason that I never hear
people say they're going web to app for
that is just they go for the fee they go
for the attribution and once they have
it they discover that oh there's also
gold over there let's go grab it so so
the last topic on on web to app uh I
want to bring up is is crossplatform is
it you know on a lot of platforms you
can specify that if they're on an
Android device they go to the the App
Store I mean to to play store if they're
on iOS they go to the App Store uh but
that's not always the case and then
there's also a lot of cases where maybe
the best experience of your product is
on a Kindle Fire or a uh set top box of
Roku or Apple TV or whatever um and so I
think the crossplatform angle of web to
app is another kind of undermentioned
reason to to build these web to app
flows yeah I guess it's not the biggest
one because uh that's not for everybody
and a lot of smaller developers very
focus on on the App Store only or App
Store and Play Store and for good reason
also for for Focus so maybe a bit more
sophisticated or or edge cases I have I
have one app in particular where for us
the Amazon app store is actually uh a
very important platform so it's not as
big as as as the app store for us in
terms of Rue but it's not it's not small
at all and I was actually very surprised
because I never I never worked with the
Amazon app store before and I was like
okay there's 50 million active users
with an Amazon tablet not even with the
phone just the tablets in the us alone
like uh and there are countries where
it's actually not very big and in Europe
we're not seeing a lot of of those
Amazon tablets but there are countries
where it's very big in Latin America for
example it's quite significant and many
because it's a bit of an edge case for
many like many platforms just don't
offer this possibility at all of sending
to the Amazon app store some and we
discovered that have the option and it
doesn't work because nobody's
maintaining it and like so it's
infuriating so obviously in this case
like uh having sort of a a browser is
interesting sometimes a little bit so it
could be like uh specific platforms like
this mentioned the Amazon store could be
also with with Huawei that has a very
big reach uh personally struggle to
monetize anything there but the the rich
is so big that for some apps with
network effects it might be of of very
high importance to be present on the
yway store and not sent to the Play
Store because some devices just cannot
have the Play Store at all uh and then
there are other other other platforms as
well you mentioned rocku there's always
but there are also cases where just you
can't so typically for example on Google
app ads you cannot select the version
that you're after and maybe your app is
just not compatible with some device and
it's not obvious in the Play Store and
and you're going to have traffic that is
going to turn at the install stage and
and it's
frustrating Google says they control
that Nott true but mostly in the
subscription space we do see that older
version on Android tend to correlate
with lower subscription rate and like oh
if only I could run my campaign only for
Android 10 plus which you can do on
Facebook but you can't do on on on
Google ads and then on the web you have
this option if you advertise on YouTube
you can say Okay I want Android 10 plus
or whatever sometimes it's even more
than that I mean when we often say oh
yeah those under device they don't
convert but actually if you zoom in like
there's big fragmentation but if you
look at the latest Google pixel phones
or the expensive some phones or
expensive xiaomi phones that are now
worth 800 1,000 and more that are really
good phone that are competing with the
iPhone in terms of quality if you zoom
in on that segment the conversion rate
they're actually not very different from
from from iPhones and and you're like
okay I want this inventory but I don't
want the rest of the inventory because I
don't manage to monetize anything on it
or just because I want to be differently
on it I can perfectly have a campaign
that is building okay here only for the
Google pixel and whatever Samsung that
has been published in the last two years
I'm going to bid X and for the rest of
device I still W that but I'm going to
bid Y and this is something that a lot
of networks don't enable us to do
because it doesn't go that I mentioned
Google but then not the other one
Facebook does enable pretty good uh
targeting there but uh there are many
platforms that don't necessarily enable
you to do this uh so I think it's a bit
more of an edge case compared to what we
mentioned before but then sometimes the
edge case become critical case for
a given app because they have a very
specific audience or because I don't
know uh because your game is so
demanding in terms of performance that
you know the experience is going to be
terrible below a certain level of device
and then so we talked about
crossplatform but even within a platform
and I think the topic are are a bit
related it can make a lot of sense to go
web to web because you have a bit more
control on this yeah are you I I just my
ignorance but in in the Google I guess
Google Google Chrome or whatever browser
they would have installed that the the
webt um or the the the web experience
would be on are you able to in the
browser actually see what version of
Android they have or or at least infer
it to where then you you split that
traffic where you send some to like in
the example of a game maybe your primary
game does have you know High
requirements and you send all the people
with a a newer device to the Play Store
to that game and maybe you send the
others to a more casual game that
doesn't have the requirements are you
able to to get that granularity on in in
the web um so yes you are it's actually
a very interesting use case that you're
that you're showing there like uh it's
going to make me think about it like uh
when you have different product I think
it's it's a very good uh tactic rather
than because you you have it twofold you
have it on targeting on the network side
where you say oh I only want this device
or oh those device I'm going to send
them there and those device I'm going to
send them there so you would usually
have to have two different campaigns
it's not like you can do that within a
campaign and tell Facebook send those
here and send those there but you can do
it on various levels one you can do it
through URL parameters and actually
sending this traffic to like so that
would be transparent for the user but
you can send the traffic towards the
server the networks they don't like when
you do redirect because a lot of
scammers are are exploiting this but
actually you could do it straight of
sending all all the device towards a URL
that DET tect the device and actually
split the traffic what is a lot more
common is that once people have landed
on your on your landing page you have
access to the device details like it's
not it's not considered as personal
information because there's an
aggregated so on it the fragmentation is
so big that you arrive there's a longer
list of device with one or two people
having this device but uh yes absolutely
you have this information it's not a
it's not a hidden information it's not
there might be times where in the future
where this information get withheld
because it can be you and it is being
used to help the accuracy of
fingerprinting at the moment this
information is still available and you
could you could devise a strategy like
you said typically the developers that I
work with what we're doing it is with
using it on the targeting side of the
network which typically when you're
using Instagram they know which device
you have like but there is nothing that
uh that prevents vents you from uh using
sending everything and and using this
information on your web page because you
have access to this information yeah a
good place for for people to experiment
with yeah
sure well we had like six topics to
discuss today we only got through web to
app but I think this has been a one of
the more insightful conversations I've
had on web to app um you certainly like
collect connected a lot of dots that
were kind of lingering in the back of my
mind and like understanding the the
reasoning the tactics you know what's
working what's not so I think this has
been super helpful and I guess we'll
have to have you back on next year to
cover the other five topics we supposed
to cover today yeah I mean we had lots
of topic I'm I'm usually happier when we
take one topic and we dig deeper because
we don't stay on the surface so I think
that was very good and I hope that uh
the the listeners will have enjoyed it
and if they're there listening to this
is that they listen to the end so I
guess mission is done but the topic is
so broad as well like even even here
within an hour or I didn't I didn't put
the the timing the timer but uh it's so
Broad and so deep that uh it's also a
very good one to open the conversation
and I I I hope that uh this this
recording is just going to be an entry
point that we can discuss more on the
sub Club forum and elsewhere none in my
linking request please but uh absolutely
openly on on slack and forums I'm always
interested to chat about this and it's
also lots of people are experimenting
with different things and um I started
doing this web to up journey in
2016 and I'm still learning so yeah
let's hope let's hope this was a an open
door for for more conversation about it
yeah that's great um anything else you
wanted to share as we're wrapping up I
know you're pretty much always booked so
uh won won't say contact Thomas if you
need help with this uh but anything else
you wanted to share is wrap up no that
I'm available on the on the Forum I
prefer to answer question publicly
because then it's one to n and what I
have to say I mean I'm not I'm not
hiding anything I'm happy to help uh I
dedicate part of my time helping like
openly for free just because I like it
and I learn a lot from it so yeah if you
if you want to reach out maybe reach out
in a public place where I'm even more
happy to do the effort that so others
can benefit from the answer and and I
don't have to repeat the same thing 20
times as well so uh yeah join us on on
sub club or you can reach me out I'm on
many open slacks for app developers like
mobile Dev memo ASO stacks and a bunch
of them like this so um yeah let's let's
get the conversation there um also
hopeful that uh it's not going to be one
to end but end to end because there's
lots of talent that has that has grown
into this this topic that can intervene
and lot more expert uh uh the ones that
are building tools the one that have
have done it for three apps so I guess
we can all learn from having an open
conversation about it yeah it's great
and yeah Thomas is really active on the
sub Club community so uh and we actually
post every episode of the podcast to the
community so if you have specific
questions on the episode feel free to
just reply to that post and tag Thomas
and we can keep the conversation going
or start a whole new topic on the sub
club uh community and we'll we'll keep
the conversation going and maybe I mean
there's probably a lot of put from those
of you listening who that you know you
were shouting into the uh ether while
you were listening in your car or
whatever saying no no no no they should
mention this or like I experimented with
that and it it actually worked really
amazing and they were saying it's no
good or whatever so uh yeah pop pop into
the sub Club Community and uh tell us
your experiences and we you know he and
I both have a ton more to learn so we'd
love to hear from y'all as well awesome
Thomas this has been so fun and uh we'll
definitely be doing it again soon yeah
thank you very much that was
great thanks so much for listening if
you have a minute please leave a review
in your favorite podcast player you can
also stop by chat. subclub do.com to
join our private community
[Music]